Finding Aid for Thomas A. Butts papers, 1961-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Thomas A. Butts papers 1961-2003, 1975-1995
Butts, Thomas A.
9 linear feet
0670 Aa
Thomas A. Butts, an expert in financial aid and student loan programs, worked for the University of Michigan, 1964-1999. He served as Director of Student Financial Aid (1971-1977), policy advisor and Deputy Assistant Secretary for Student Financial Assistance for the federal government (1977-1981), and was responsible for government relations for the University of Michigan at the Washington D.C. office (1991-1999). The collection documents his work for the University of Michigan admissions office, office of orientation, office of financial aid, and Washington D.C. office of government relations, his work for the U.S. Department of Education, and the evolution of federal student financial aid legislation.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received in several accessions (donor nos. 8564 and 7446 ].
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Thomas Butts devoted his career to improving student financial aid and loan programs. He first worked for the University of Michigan from 1964 to 1977. He was an admissions counselor, 1964-1966; Assistant Director of Admissions, 1966-1967; Director of Student Orientation, 1967-1977; Assistant Director of ERIC (Educational Resources Information Center) and CAPS (Counseling and Personnel Services), 1967-1977, and Director of Student Financial Aid, 1971-1977.
While he was Director of Financial Aid, Thomas Butts was involved with the National Task Force on Student Aid Problems, a short-term working group charged with analyzing the process of applying for financial aid. It was active from May 1974 to July 1975. Thomas Butts was chair of the Working Committee for Common Form, which was involved in designing and testing a nation-wide form for applying for financial aid. The Task Force became the National Student Aid Coalition in 1975, and Thomas Butts served as the chair of the Committee on Need Analysis and Delivery, 1975-1977.
In 1977, he took a leave of absence from the University of Michigan and served the federal government, from 1977 to 1981. He was a policy advisor for Student Financial Assistance, under the U.S. Office of Education, from 1977 to 1979. He then served as the Deputy Assistant Secretary for Student Assistance from 1979 to 1981, and was Acting Deputy Commissioner during the establishment of the Education Department. He was also involved in several task forces and committees dealing with specific issues at the time, including the reauthorization of the Higher Education Act, and was called upon to testify before congressional subcommittees.
In 1981, he returned to the employ of the University of Michigan, where he remained until his retirement in 1999. He worked out of the university's Washington D.C. office, and was active in student loan legislation issues. He was the Government Relations Officer, 1981-1991; Executive Director of the Washington D.C. Office, 1990-1999; and Associate Vice President for Government Relations, 1991-1999. During this time, he was very active in promoting legislation for the Direct Loan Program. He also served as an adjunct faculty member for the Center for Higher and Postsecondary Education, from 1990 to 1999.
This collection would be of use for research into the role of Thomas Butts at the University of Michigan, the role of the University of Michigan in student financial aid policy, and the evolution of federal student loan policy generally. The collection is composed of six series. The first five correspond to the positions Thomas Butts held (Office of Admissions, Office of Orientation, Office of Financial Aid, U.S. Department of Education, and Washington D.C. Office) and a sixth series, Loans, contains information on specific loan programs. The Loans series especially provides insight into how laws are developed in the federal government, including the evolution of the Higher Education Act and the Direct Loan program. Thomas Butts was involved with many organizations, and a glossary of the main acronyms follows the scope and content note.
Subjects:
Butts, Thomas A.; Student financial aid--United States.; Student aid--United States.; Student loans--United States.; University of Michigan--Admissions.; University of Michigan. Office of Financial Aid.; University of Michigan. Office of Orientation.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Government Relations.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.; Audiocassettes.
- Office of Admissions
  Office of Admissions series (0.1 linear feet, 1966-1967) covers the testing and improvement of the new computer system AC-PAA (Admissions Computer-Profile Analysis Assist), used to process applications, which was implemented while Thomas Butts was the Assistant Director of Admissions. There are also examples of form letters for acceptance, wait-list for acceptance, and rejection letters.
  - Resumes of Thomas Butts (includes later cvs) (Box 1)
  - How to Process Applications Workflow 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - AC-PAA (Admissions Computer-Profile Analysis Assist) Computer System, Types of Data Collected 1966 (Box 1)
  - AC-PAA Computer System, Evaluating and Modifying the System 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Form Acceptance and Rejection Letters 1967 (Box 1)
- Office of Orientation
  Office of Orientation series (0.5 linear feet, 1968-1975 and 2000) is mostly composed of papers on the professional organizations that Thomas Butts was a member of, or participated in conferences, during his time as the Director of Student Orientation and after. He was a presenter at many conferences (including ACPA, HEEA, MCPA, MPGA, New Directions, and AACRAO). The 1971 AACRAO speech is on audio cassette. Thomas Butts also served on the ACPA Commission II School-College Relations, Admissions and Orientation from 1970 to 1973. Also of note are evaluations of the program by participants and student leaders in 1968 and 1969, and two publications by Thomas Butts: "Freshman Placement" and "What is Orientation?" from 1969. Thomas Butts stayed in contact with the orientation community even after he left the position, and attended the AACRAO annual meeting in 2000.
  - Survey of Orientation Programs undated (Box 1)
  - Program Evaluation by Transfer Students 1968 (Box 1)
  - Program Evaluation by Orientation Leaders 1968-1969, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Publications by Thomas Butts: "Freshman Placement" and "What is Orientation?" 1969 (Box 1)
  - Conferences
    - National Orientation Director's Conference "New Directions in Orientation," 1970 (Box 1)
    - Higher Education Executive Associates (HEEA) "College Orientation Programs in the 1970s" 1970 (Box 1)
    - American Association of Collegiate Registrars and Admission Officers (AACRAO) Annual Meeting 1970-1971, 2000 (Box 1)
    - AACRAO, Thomas Butts' Speeches 1971 (Box 1)
      (2 audio cassette tapes)
    - ACT/CSS 1972 (Box 1)
      (5 audio cassette tapes)
  - Membership
    - American College Personnel Association (ACPA) 1969-1972 (Box 1)
    - ACPA Commission II: School-College Relations, Admissions, and Orientation 1969-1975 (Box 1)
    - American Professional Development Associates (APDA) 1971 (Box 1)
    - American Personnel and Guidance Association (APGA) 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Michigan College Personnel Association (MCPA) 1967-1971 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Personnel and Guidance Association (MPGA) 1966-1971 (Box 1)
  - Camp Michigania, Alumni Association Camp 1965-1970 (Box 1)
- Office of Financial Aid
  Office of Financial Aid (OFA) series (3.4 linear feet, 1971-1978 and 1999-2001) documents the development of his interest in student financial aid and loan issues, and his increased involvement with the financial aid community. The series is divided into six subseries. The first three cover the activities of the University of Michigan financial aid office. The last three cover Thomas Butts' participation in the wider financial aid community.
  - Student Loan Programs
    "Student Loan Programs" (0.5 linear feet) are Thomas Butts' papers as the Director of Financial Aid. The original order and labeling of the folders have been maintained. They cover the major issues facing the office, including programs, privacy, and minority enrollment. A sociology honors thesis includes an interview with Thomas Butts and his notes on the final product.
    - Applying for Financial Aid 1972 (Box 1)
    - Sociology Honors Thesis "The Inhibition of Motivation and Achievement in Black Opportunity Program Students," 1974 (Box 1)
      (includes Thomas Butts interview and annotations)
    - Internal Policy Committee 1974 (Box 1)
    - Establishing Agreements with Private Lenders 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - Minority Projections since BAM (Black Action Movement) 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - National Merit Program 1973 (Box 1)
    - Federal Financial Aid 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Audit Reports on Student Loans 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - Release of Student Information 1970-1972 (Box 1)
    - State Financial Aid Budget Request 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - Work Study Program 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - State Financial Aid 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Total Student Aid Expenditures 1972-1974 (Box 1)
    - Guaranteed Bank Loan and Federally Insured Loan 1971-1974 (Box 2)
    - FISAP Workshop 1980 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    "Correspondence" (0.3 linear feet) includes alphabetical files of communications between the OFA and parents, which document the daily routine of the OFA, and the University of Michigan response to the budget cuts of 1982. Thomas Butts stayed active in the financial aid community after leaving the position, so there is also a file of correspondence between university financial aid officers from 1999.
    - Alphabetical 1966-1979, 7 folders (Box 2)
    - Letters of Appreciation for Thomas Butts 1965-1966 (Box 2)
    - Thomas Butts presents at the Indiana First Regional Campus Orientation Workshop 1973 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan's Reaction to Federal Budget Cuts 1982 (Box 2)
    - Between Universities 1999 (Box 2)
  - Publications
    "Publications" (0.3 linear feet) contains printed materials from loan providers and evaluations and research on loan programs. Of special note is the report by MSFAA on the Needs Analysis program tested at the University of Michigan in 1973. This section also includes newspaper clippings regarding the University of Michigan's inability to meet minority enrollment standards and a financial aid controversy surrounding the refusal of a scholarship to a 14-year-old genius because he did not demonstrate financial need (1973). Publications by Thomas Butts focus on student services and counseling students.
    - Financial Aid Programs: "Overview of Current Efforts" and "Institutional Guide for Financial Aid Self-Evaluation," 1977 (Box 2)
    - Loan Information for Financial Aid Administrators 1961-1977, 1998 (Box 2)
    - Loan Information for Students 1971, 1999 (Box 2)
    - Midwest Association of Student Financial Aid Administrators (MASFAA) Newsletter 1971 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Student Financial Aid Association (MSFAA) Report of the Ad Hoc Committee to Review State of Michigan Financial Aid Programs 1973 (Box 2)
    - MSFAA Evaluation of the American College Testing Program and the College Scholarship Service Need Analysis Systems 1973-1974 (Box 2)
    - National Council of Higher Education Loan Programs (NCHELP), Lender Services Guide and Membership List 1986 (Box 2)
    - NCHELP Research Papers 1985, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings on Black Enrollment, the Middle Income Crunch, and Declaring Independence at Age 18 1973 (Box 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings on Greg Wellman, a 14-year-old Genius denied a scholarship at the University of Michigan 1973 (Box 2)
    - Student Services and Student Counseling, by Thomas Butts 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - MHEAA/MSFAA Survey Data
    "MHEAA/MSFAA Survey Data" (0.3 linear feet) is the survey forms filled out by Michigan universities regarding their financial aid programs. There were two surveys: one of vocational schools in 1977, and one of undergraduate programs at degree granting institutions in 1979. The forms for each survey are arranged alphabetically. The undergraduate survey includes data from University of Michigan Dearborn and Flint, but not Ann Arbor.
    - Vocational School Student Financial Aid Survey 1977, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Undergraduate Student Aid for Michigan Degree Granting Colleges and Universities 1978, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - MASFAA Annual Conference 1977 (Box 3)
  - National Task Force on Student Aid Problems
    "National Task Force on Student Aid Problems" (0.5 linear feet, 1974-1976) includes records of meetings of the entire task force, including the notes of Thomas Butts, and records from meetings of different working committees. Most of the papers are from the "Working Committee on Common Form," which was involved in creating a prototype financial aid application that could be used for all institutions. Thomas Butts was chairman of the committee from 1974-1975.
    - Organizing the Task Force 1974 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1974-1975 (Box 3)
      (coordinating and justifying the task force)
    - Chicano Group 1975 (Box 3)
      (explaining their position to the task force)
    - College Entrance Exam Board (CEEB) 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Thomas Butt's notes on Meetings and Calls 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - General Task Force Meeting Agendas and Minutes 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Working Committee on Common Form
      - Correspondence 1974-1975 (Box 3)
      - Meeting Minutes 1974-1975 (Box 3)
      - Statements and Reports 1974-1975 (Box 3)
      - Common Form Prototypes 1974-1975 (Box 3)
      - Financial Aid Application Forms in use 1974-1975 (Box 3)
      - Budget and Negotiations with Field Testers 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Working Committee on Coordination and Management 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Working Committee on Needs Analysis 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Keppel Task Force Follow Through Committee 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Final Report 1975, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - National Association of Student Financial Aid Administrators (NASFAA)
    "NASFAA" (1.0 linear feet, 1976-1977 and 2000-2001) includes the meetings and recommendations of various committees, records on defining what an independent student is, and the guidebook for president-elect, Thomas Butts, from 1977. There are also records on the structure, meetings, and recommendations of the National Council. He was a member of the organization throughout his career, and attended the annual meetings in 2000 and 2001.
    - National Council Guidebook for President-Elect, Thomas Butts 1977 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1977, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Newsletters 1971, 1979, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes 1977 (Box 3)
    - Establishing Committee on New Legislation 1977 (Box 3)
    - Finance Committee 1977 (Box 3)
    - Commission on Minority Affairs 1977 (Box 3)
    - Defining "Independent Student," 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Financial Aid Consulting Service 1977 (Box 3)
    - National Council Meeting 1977 (Box 3)
    - Loan to Parents Program 1978 (Box 3)
    - Annual Conference 2000-2001, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - National Council
      - Structure and Membership 1976-1977 (Box 4)
      - Coordinating Council Activities 1976-1977 (Box 4)
      - Meeting Minutes 1976-1977 (Box 4)
      - Reports and Recommendations 1976 (Box 4)
- U.S. Department of Education
  U.S. Department of Education series (1.0 linear feet, 1977-1987) covers the time when Thomas Butts worked for the federal government, as part of the U.S. Department of Education. He was most involved in the Office of Student Financial Assistance, where he was acting deputy commissioner for a time. Records include correspondence and reports of activities. The bulk of the records are correspondence files from 1978 and 1979, which reveal the daily routine of the U.S. Department of Education and involve many organizations and individuals voicing their opinions, as well as the response of the U.S. Department of Education. Most of the correspondence is of Ernest Boyer, U.S. Commissioner of Education, and Leo Kornfeld, Deputy Commissioner for Student Financial Assistance, then forwarded to Thomas Butts.
  - Structure of Department 1981 (Box 4)
  - Executive Operations Staff Meeting Notes 1980 (Box 4)
  - "Operation Common Sense," Rewriting Regulations into Plain English 1977 (Box 4)
  - Lending Institution Regional Training Effort 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - Monthly Correspondence 1978, 13 folders (Box 4)
  - Monthly Correspondence 1979, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Office of Student Financial Assistance
    - Department Goals and Budgets 1982 (Box 4)
    - Reports of Activities 1977-1980 (Box 4)
    - Publications 1979-1980, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1977-1981 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence Congratulating Thomas Butts for New Appointments 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - National Appeal Panel 1981 (Box 4)
  - Thomas Butts Resignation 1981 (Box 4)
- Washington D.C. Office (University of Michigan)
  Washington D.C. Office (0.75 linear feet, 1982-2001). During this time, Thomas Butts was again working directly for the University of Michigan, in Washington D.C. as the Vice President for Government Relations. It is divided into 7 sections.
  "Office" includes records on the mission, staff, and budget of the Washington D.C. office. It also includes a list of University of Michigan alumni at Washington D.C. for 1985 to 1986.
  "National Student Aid Coalition" (0.25 linear feet, 1981-1987). It is a descendent of the National Task Force. Records from the coalition as a whole include meeting minutes, reports, and correspondence. Also included are records from the Committee on Need Assessment and Delivery, of which Thomas Butts was chair from 1975 to 1977, that include meeting minutes, and a report on uniform methodology from 1987.
  "Committees" (0.4 linear feet, 1993-2001) includes the Ad Hoc Tax Committee, the Coalition of Statue University Aid Administrators (COSUAA), and the Lobbying Disclosure Act Task Force, of which Thomas Butts was chair in 1996. The majority of the records pertain to the Advisory Committee on Student Financial Assistance, which was an independent committee created by Congress to advise on student aid policy. These include reports advising Congress on financial aid matters and a controversy involving conflicts of interest with the members of the committee that lead to the resignation of Thomas Butts.
  "HACE Seminar" covers an annual seminar taught by Thomas Butts for the Higher and Continuing Education program of the University of Michigan. They were held from 1990 to 1994, taking place half in Ann Arbor and half at Washington D.C., and covering current issues in financial aid. These included the reauthorization of the higher education act and funding education under the Clinton Administration. The records include course descriptions and lists of the individuals visited at Washington D.C. by the class. There are also a few letters of praise from students in the correspondence file.
  "Conferences" includes papers from three conferences that Thomas Butts was involved in. He gave a presentation to the Ohio Association of Student Financial Aid Administrators on politics in 1982, participated in a Roundtable on Distance Learning in 1998, and lectured on lobbying techniques at the Michigan Student Financial Aid Association (MSFAA) in 2001.
  "Correspondence with UM Ann Arbor" consists of Thomas Butts communicating with the University of Michigan to explain issues from Washington D.C. These include both the implications of new bills and budgets, and the actions of specific senators. It also includes Ann Arbor administrators expressing their concerns to Washington D.C., and Thomas Butts providing assistance in searching for a professor from Turkey to come to the Ann Arbor campus.
  "Thomas Butts' Activities" are records of Thomas Butts participating in the financial aid community. These include being a guest speaker, reviewing papers and financial aid programs for other universities, and receiving an award.
  - Mission and Staff 1989-1998 (Box 5)
  - Office Budget 1993-1995 (Box 5)
  - University of Michigan Alumni at Washington D.C. 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - American Council on Education (ACE) Report "The Impact of Significant Federal Student Loan Policy Changes and the Role of States in Student Credit," 1993 (Box 5)
  - National Student Aid Coalition
    - Mission and History 1984-1987 (Box 5)
    - Internal Communication 1981 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1984 (Box 5)
    - Reports 1982-1985 (Box 5)
    - Meeting Minutes 1984-1985 (Box 5)
    - Committee on Need Assessment and Delivery, Meeting Minutes 1981-1987, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Committee on Need Assessment and Delivery, Report on Uniform Methodology 1987 (Box 5)
  - Ad Hoc Tax Committee (Box 5)
  - Advisory Committee on Student Financial Assistance (ACSFA)
    - Meetings and Reports 1991, 2000-2001 (Box 5)
    - Advising Congress 1994-1995 (Box 5)
    - Conflict of Interest Within the Committee 1994-1995 (Box 5)
    - Developing a Member Code of Conduct 1994-1995 (Box 5)
  - Coalition of State University Aid Administrators (COSUAA) 1999-2001 (Box 5)
  - Lobbying Disclosure Act Task Force 1996 (Box 5)
    (Thomas Butts, chair)
  - Higher and Continuing Education (HACE) Seminar on Washington Postsecondary Education Policy 1990-1993, 5 folders (Box 5)
    (taught by Thomas Butts)
  - Conferences
    - Ohio Association of Student Financial Aid Administrators (OASFAA) Spring Conference 1982 (Box 5)
      (Thomas Butts presents on politics)
    - Roundtable on Distance Learning 1998 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Student Financial Aid Association (MSFAA) 2001 (Box 5)
      (Thomas Butts lectures on lobbying techniques)
  - Thomas Butts Correspondence with University of Michigan
    - Employee Educational Assistance Act H.R. 2568, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Congressman Wolpe and the National Science Foundation 1991 (Box 5)
    - Federal Budget Situation 1995-1996 (Box 5)
    - Search for Turkish Professor for the University of Michigan 1996 (Box 5)
  - Thomas Butts' Activities
    - Guest Lecturer for a University of Michigan Public Policy Class 1988 (Box 6)
    - Reviewing the University of Wisconsin's Financial Aid Program 1989 (Box 6)
    - Speaker at the Colorado Student Leadership Symposium: Reauthorization of the Higher Education Act 1991 (Box 6)
    - Reviewing a Paper for Ramapo College of New Jersey 1999 (Box 6)
    - Awards and Thank You Notes 1999-2000 (Box 6)
- Loans
  Loans series (3.25 linear feet, 1968-2003) is the only series not tied to where Thomas Butts was working at the time. It covers issues pertaining to loan programs over time, and provides a look at how laws and programs are created and evolve at the federal level. The most significant student loan legislation is the Higher Education Act (HEA), which was established in 1965, and reauthorized in 1972, 1980, 1986, 1992, and 1998. The two other main student loan programs in this collection, the Guaranteed Student Loan and the Direct Student Loan programs, are both part of the Higher Education Act. Thomas Butts was particularly involved with advocating the Direct Loan Program. It was created in 1993, and began operation in the 1994/1995 academic year, to be studied in a 5 year program. Loans is divided into 7 subseries.
  - Overview
    "Overview" subseries (0.2 linear feet and 2 VHS tapes) provides summary information about a wide range of loan programs. These include program descriptions, interest rates, and articles. The two videos are of Congressman Wolpe on Nightline, 1992, and the Future of Financial Aid, 1995.
    - Characteristics of Loan Programs 1977, 1999 (Box 6)
    - Cost of Loan Programs 1979, 1999 (Box 6)